so in this suta maim manika
78 the Buddha is
discussing uh the view of a surge
aesthetic uh who basically says
this is this was his statement Carpenter
when a man possesses four qualities I
describe him as accomplished in what is
wholesome perfected in what is wholesome
an aesthetic Invincible attained to the
Supreme attainment what are the four
here he does no evil bodily actions he
utters no evil speech he has no evil
intentions and he does not make his
living by any evil livelihood when a man
possesses these four qualities I
describe is accomplished in what is
wholesome perfected in what is wholesome
as an aesthetic Invincible attain to the
Supreme attainment that was the
statement of this aesthetic and then the
Buddha replied to it
with if that were so then a young tender
infant lying prone is accomplished in
what is wholesome perfected in what is
wholesome an aesthetic Invincible
attained to the Supreme attainment
according to the wand ugana statement
for a young tender tender infant lying
prone does does not even have the notion
body so how should he do an evil bodily
action Beyond mere rling a young tender
infant lying prone does not even have
the notion speech so how should he utter
evil speech Beyond near whining a young
tender infant lying prone does not even
have the notion intention so how should
he have evil intentions beyond beyond
mere sulking a young young tender infant
ly prown does not even have the notion
livelihood so how should he make his
living by evil livelihood beyond beyond
being suckled at his mother's breast if
that were so Carpenter then a young
tender infant lying prone is
accomplished in what is
wholesome and uh so the Buddha is
basically refuting here the idea that
just because you don't do stuff externally
because you don't do stuff externally
that doesn't mean that you are already
accomplished and wholesome and then
further on he says
what are UNH wholesome he he goes on to
Define what what are the actual un
wholesome habits and he says they are
UNH wholesome bodily actions UNH
wholesome verbal actions and evil
livelihood but then he describes what do
these UNH wholesome habits originate
from and he says they should be said to
originate from mind what mind though
mind is multiple varied and of different
aspects there is mind affected by lust
by aversion and by melness or delusion
un wholesome habits originate from this
and then how does he Define wholesome
habits he says they should also be said
to originate from mind uh though mind is
multiple varied and of different aspects
there is mind not affected by Lust by
aversion or by delusion wholesome habits
originate from
this so the idea here is
so the idea here is
that even though a person might not be
outwardly performing any of the UNH
wholesome actions like that tender
infant for example um wholesomeness
doesn't depend on that it depends on the
on the mind so that tender infant even
though he's not doing anything his mind
has the underlying tendency to blust a
virgin and delusion even though it's not
being um ouly expressed in in these CH
ways so that leads us then to the point
so that leads us then to the point
of what is wholesome and un wholesome
like um can a
um can a
person because you know we we talk about
undertaking The Virtue the sense
restraint and that sort of thing but
it's easy to then think that
wholesomeness isn't just doing this
undertaking this Behavior as opposed
to uh what you whatever you used to be
doing before
so how can you know then
that your
behavior is not
just emulating the behavior of an Arun but is
emulating the behavior of an Arun but is
actually matching it on that level that
matters that is actually developing your
mind because that's what's wholesome is
so how how can you know whether your
action body speech and mind are
wholesome can you just follow a
prescribed set of rules or observances
defined by someone even the Buddha
himself like would following for example
the whole
V in its entirety to exp Perfection
ensure that you are um committing
wholesome and
it doesn't guarantee that
yeah so how but how how then could you
tell I am doing something UNH wholesome
now let's say you avoided the course
stuff by undertaking the eight precepts
So within that what is UNH wholesome
then apart from the obvious actions that
you're not doing anymore
is it that for example studying
dhama or meditating is automatically
wholesome because it's about D uhhuh now
that doesn't follow either yeah and also
these eight precepts you know about not
killing not stealing not taking toxicant
and so on um that is on the level of
behavior that can be seen even from the
outside but
um whether something is wholesome or UNH
wholesome has to do with that very basis
or mind that gives rise to Wholesome un
wholesome actions and essentially it it
has to do with um the intentions based
on which one is
acting and that is a let's say a
dimension Beyond um external behavior that one
Beyond um external behavior that one
needs
to uh come to terms to by oneself
basically like everyone has a privileged
position to not only see themselves
doing what they're doing but to
simultaneously see why they are doing
what they're
doing and what is that why more
specifically is it like if I ask you why
are you doing this yeah and then the
answer you give me is
that like let's say I ask you why are
you doing this and you give me a
satisfactory answer
does that mean it's wholesome no because
somebody can still so reasons and
arguments here could still be um like
well the weather was nice so I decided
to do it or or or which might be a
reason but that is not very the
intentions are so for example um if one
is acting out of one of the five
hindrances um that would be un wholesome
just just to give an indication um um or
or more generally greed hatred and
illusion to the extent that one has
understood greed hatred and illusion one
should refrain from acting out of that
um so um it would depend on
understanding those things and keeping
them in mind so
mind so
then does do those five hindrances have
specific places where they arise like
only here I'm going to experience
this like spec only would they arise
only in specific context
B would the five hindrances only arise
in specific
contexts what do you mean by arise in
this Cas like taking the hindrances not
as instances
of acting out but as the underlying tend
yeah just Cally speaking or you could
take it as greed aversion and delusion
is it is it something that only comes up
in specific instances or specific
situations well I guess I mean as the
suta says it's it's an underlying
tendency so maybe the obvious kind of
indications that they're present might
only come up from time to time
but the fact that they were able to come
up indicates that yeah
tendency was there thought that's kind
of just repeating what was said yeah so
like the point I'm trying to make is
that obviously um there will be things
that uh are more strongly bound up with
those hindrances but fundamentally or
with the defant in general but
fundamentally those things form like the
background of your experience in any
situation yes so that means that there
is nothing that you can rest
assured that this is not un wholesome
that this won't be underlied by one of
these un wholesome intentions like that
like that's why I mentioned dhama for
example many people might not
necessarily realize that things like um
you know studying dama or meditating or
know studying dama or meditating or
making effort towards the practice can
be underlied by those same intentions
which means by those same UNH wholesome
intentions of longing
aversion U indolence
restlessness anxiety doubt and that's
what makes it un wholesome yes not
because like this is about dhama and
this other the thing is about mundane
stuff uh then this is wholesome and this
is UN wholesome it's anything that is
underlined by that mental state any
anything that is underlied by a mind
that um that craves really like for
anything doesn't matter what it is for
or against yeah for or against uh that
is UN wholesome because of that not
because of the kind of properties of how
you describe what you're doing MH so
that means that
um even the intention that you might
State as I am doing this because of such
and such like you said because the
weather is nice or something even that
would be underline underlain
by that level of a hindrance by the
level of your mind pulling you towards
something and you giving into that mhm
and that's what makes it it it doesn't
matter what it might even be like I
don't know um doing something that the
Buddha himself told you to do or like
the most wholesome kind of activity you
could imagine M even then you would be
increasing you would be going in the
direction of un wholesome if your mind
at that that time is underlined by these
states M and you're proliferating them
so that means that
then the kind of carefulness that has to
be employed is not on the level
of um the usual you know when MX would
really try really hard to protect the V
for example it would be kind of
directed almost outwardly like the
external properties of how I do this
when I do it um like what in what
condition this is appropriate in what
condition is it not appropriate and then
basically all that means is that you
would never be able to be free from
doubt in regard to your own virtue and
in regard to your wholesomeness and UNH
wholesomeness because somebody else may
come along and say no no that in that
context you shouldn't have done this you
should have done something else so then
at any point
that could be undermined by something
that you didn't know like if if virtue
depended on like making the right choice
in that external sense M at any point um
like it it could be proven what you did
could be proven wrong but if it always
depends only on your state of mind then
the whole world can come and tell you
you made a mistake and you know that
that's not the case like it's a mistake
in a worldly sense sure but in the sense
of acting out of craving you would be
able to
100% uh with 100% certainty say no I did
not act out of craving I did not commit
an offense in this in the context of
dhma so that's what um the kind of a
accomplishment in virtue that that a
person should develop and that's really
what um extreme entry is it's the
ability to have that perfect certainty
of wholesome and un wholesome and most
importantly regr tot like because your
virtue doesn't depend anymore on the
things that on the world or or anything that
that on the world or or anything that
was predefined it doesn't even depend on
your information that you gain from the
dhama like the the the the rules that
you learned or the the habits that you
developed it depends only on knowing
what is your state of mind and then not
acting out of that yeah so so even the
consequence even the worldly
consequences of Cl actions they might
turn out to be somewhat unfortunate yeah
and people might criticize someone for
that but that is then understood as okay
that's unfortunate but that that is not
what constitutes a fault in terms of
dhama yeah so then you yeah exactly you
you is basically essential to abandon
the view that uh good actions will
result in happiness in that immediate
sense like if I do something good it
should you know result in in good
consequences because
well if you don't have the right view
you don't know what the right type of
happiness is to begin with so the
happiness that you would expect to come
from your actions is still going to be
on the on the external level like you
would expect uh you know pain not to
come to you but really the happiness
that necessarily comes from virtue is
the happiness of uh not being bothered
even if bad things happen so that's a
that's a different that's a different
thing that's the blame L yeah of the
accomplishment of virtue yeah yeah so
um can I ask a question maybe it's a
little bit like of a step back but just
to clarify like let's say like someone
just learn about the precept respect
them like practicing sense strength and
then he's like learning about the the
Dharma and he try his best to go in that
direction and then he's also asking this
a question like why am I doing that but
then like the answer is not like so
clear for him like about is it whome or
is it unome like even if he's asking
himself like generally like is it like
actually whome what I'm doing is not
like 100% sure like is there is a way to
actually be sure that what he's doing is
aesome or is it
unome yeah well the the only way to be
sure would be to see the signs of the
mind which is basically the kind of a
it's inextricably linked with the Right
View like being able to
see the domain of your mind where greed
Aion and delusion is like being able to
see that clearly would mean
that nobody can tell you it works both
ways nobody can tell you um that what
you did was UNH wholesome when it was
wholesome and at the same time when
you're doing something UNH wholesome you
wouldn't need any sort of external
confirmation or somebody else to tell
you yes it was UNH wholesome you would
know uh for yourself so uh the doubt
that a person might have is not because
like they haven't like learned enough in
that kind of external sense or they
haven't like um gained enough experience
or something like that it's more like in
their own mind there is this um they
have not developed the discernment of
that domain even though it's already
there like it's not like Greer version
delusion is not there if you're not
thinking about it it is there it's just
that until a person gains that that
discernment then everywhere everywhere that they
then everywhere everywhere that they
might be looking won't be that place
where be original delusion is so then
that's why they would experience doubt
and the doubt would be there because
still on
some subtle level they would still
expect like
the confirmation to
be as given by like an external set of
rules or or relations between things
like uh was this
thing um like in a worldly sense let's
put it this way let's say um
you you dropped a a rock from a cliff
and then it killed someone accidentally
that that the one of the examples we
were discussing recently and then you
would have doubt like oh but I I
shouldn't have done that because and
then that would only happen if you
thought if if you kind of overlooked or
weren't 100% sure about the fact that
the only thing that mattered was the
state of mind that you had that that
time why did you throw the rock did you
do it because you were careless did you
do it because you were angry did you do
it because or some other reason mhm and
then if it was out of carelessness if it
was out of anger uh there would be no
room for doubt because you don't know
what I did what I did was wrong mhm
whether the person died or not because
see that that wouldn't that wouldn't be
what determined the action as un
wholesome it was the mental state that
you had when you threw the rock so then
yeah doubt would not apply and then if
you knew no I threw the rock because I
don't know it was blocking the way and I
was genuinely just trying to cross that
path then even if your mind would try to
to convince you and and try to haunt you
with guilt like no I shouldn't have done
that I shouldn't have done that you
would know nope I did that
out of an intention that was not un
wholesome and then if if my mind is
trying to make me feel guilt that's just
a hindrance and I know that I shouldn't
give into that because then basically
like if you'd have to worry about how
your mind will react to things then or
if you use that as a measure of what's
wholesome and un wholesome then I mean
the mind can the mind is going to feel
uncomfortable with um non- great non
averion non delusion by nature and it's
going to try to trick you to to uh
either do more than it's necessary or do
less than is necessary so you can't even
trust your own mind to be um responding
nicely when you when you avoid un
wholesome so you could think of it as
like if you have um
if you have a
child and uh you know the child might be
throwing Tantrums every now and
then and your goal is to teach that
child not to do that to behave properly
MH so the problem is not when you let
the like the problem is not that the
child wants to go to the park for
example the problem is that the child is
throwing a tant for you to let him go go
into the go to the park so in this case
putting aside the a precepts of course
because doing that automatically whether
you like it or not is going to involve
in in an wholesome state of mind but for
everything else what matters is is my
mind throwing a tantrum on account of
this like to let me do it if I do give
in I am uh feeding and and promoting
that bad habit
you mean if the parent throws a tantrum
then the child is no no if the child
throws a tantrum and then the parent
lets him have what he wants oh I see as
a result of the Tantrum like the child
would is the mind and you are the parent
let's say okay I see uhuh so then um
that is what makes something UNH
wholesome it's like the tantrum that the
mind was
throwing giving into that and promoting
that sort of behavior is what's making
you liable to suffering in the future
because some something will come along
some situation will come along that
either as as as The First Noel truth
would say you will be either United with
what you don't like or separated from
what you like and then the mind will be
throwing a tantrum on account of that
why because in the past whenever
something similar happened like you let
it uh act out either towards pleasure or
away from pain so in the future when
pleasure comes that sort of habit that
you you've been building up is is going
to be greater by that much by the amount
that you've been building it so it's UNH
wholesome um because it's increasing
your own liability to suffering not
because of some other kind of external
definition of what the Buddha said un
wholesome is is because it is making you
factually and
genuinely liable to the to the habits of
your own mind that's what undermines
your safety basically
because like the world is not in your
control things can happen that you don't
expect and then if your mind depends on
having the world be a certain way
because you have been allowing it to to
increase that dependency through these
actions like when pleasure comes you you
need to seek it and when pain comes you
need to run away from it then that's how
much you will be suffering when the
world keeps doing what it does MH so
it's not the fault of the world it's the
fact that you have been
um training your mind to to uh in the
opposite of the right direction that was
your being G that is your being yeah
yeah that's that that's going to be like
under underlying
underlying
your like you you once you have built
that up you can't even you can't choose
to get out of it that is that is your
reality now you have a mind that has
these habits and then you have to undo
it kind of uh indect irly you can't you
never will be able to
to just lock the child up and say no you
can't do anything anymore no you can't
so how to then undo that like one finds
oneself already with certain
habits uh and now there comes to
realization that's not in my welfare so
from now on I shouldn't give into those
habits but they're still wise yeah so
well with the same example like you have
a child that
um that's throwing a tanm to go to the
park but it's not throwing a tan trim to
I don't
know have his his dinner M like he he's
still crying he's still crying about the
park but if you if you say no no now
you're not going to have dinner you're
not going to have anything you're going
to you're going to lock it up in the
room with dark windows and like yeah
that will be a punishment of some sort
that's not going to be training it to to
Really kind of get rid of that that
habit so what you have to do is
recognize even if I choose not to do
anything that will be my choice like if
if in trying to restrain my un wholesome
habits I go too far in the direction of
no now I won't do anything well that's
not going to be like you're going to be
doing that out of the same kind of
aversion to the situation so what you
have to do is recognize no I can do
everything else except accept the thing
that the mind is craving for mhm
everything else obviously without
breaking the precepts so uh and then it
becomes very clear like uh you don't
need a um some specific definition of
what to do all you need to know is what
you shouldn't do MH that's all that
matters like don't give into this pull
to this pressure while it's there and
everything else you can do so if you
have um I don't know Central in your
mind for example uh that doesn't mean
that you need to like again close
everything and and and lock yourself up
or get in concentration state so to free
yourself from that it means you can have
you can think about anything you can
think about you
know I don't know what you have to do
tomorrow or something like but as long
as it's not fueling the same lust that's
there and you if you um keep up with
that practice you're going to see
actually there's always a lot of space
mhm whenever an un wholesome state is
there there's always a lot of space for
you to do other things that are not
going to be rooted in that so um it's
just but in the beginning because the
mind starts out as we said with that uh
Habit of being absorbed in um greed
aversion of delusion then it's going to
feel like no no like like it's the only
thing you have in your experience that
you can't do anything else but really
there's always infinite amount of things
like that that um that on that occasion
would be sort of independent of
Oppression yeah it's so you have to see
it as like how can I act in not like how
can I stop myself from doing anything
but how can I act in a way that is
parallel to the feeling that is there m
parallel meaning you're not kind of like
uh acting out of it of out of the desire
to interfere with it but no the feeling
is there and I'm not trying to get rid
of it the pressure and then this action
is kind of happening at the same time
without being directed at the feeding
either for or against so you're having
Central thoughts and then you decide to
go for a walk so is that walk going to
be making you indulge in those Central
thoughts no like if you start indulging
in central thoughts that's not because
of the Walk that's because you went for
a walk and decided to give into the
central thoughts and at the same time
it's not going to be rooted in running
away from it m because you're not um
you're not trying to suppress them
you're not trying to to kind of escape
from it in that in that um direct manner
out of a verion so you can go for a walk
and then if the central thought persist
throughout the entire walk well so be it
because that's that's your com like
that's the Habit these things are
happening because of the tendencies that
you've been proliferating from before MH
so yeah you just endure it as the Buddha
said you U refrain from from putting in
the fuel like is it's as if there was a fire
fuel like is it's as if there was a fire
burning M and a man would not be
throwing sticks and and leaves and dry
leaves into it it doesn't say like the
man kind of you know takes I don't know
yeah yeah because that would be again
interfering with it so you let it burn
for as long as it for as long as it has
been um for as long as the fuel is there
for it to burn and then yeah that's the
way to get has to go out that's the way
to get rid of things so uh and that's
that that where the Buddha talks about
um the five ways to get rid of your
thoughts how people translate it yes
it's like it says
um uh when when your mind is being
overwhelmed by thoughts of desire verion
and delusion it says you attend to a
different sign that is connected with
the wholesome MH that people would think
that means no I need to attend to a
different sign so as to get rid of this
kind of the whole thing that I'm
experiencing but no it means you just
find find something that
isn't going to be rooted in trying to
get rid or trying to Delight in that
same thing that's that's uh assailing
you and
then then it says as he does that those
un wholesome states are abandoned M it
doesn't say that be that like by
focusing on the different thing that's
how you immediately get rid of yeah so
so we should clear up that abandoning un
whome state does does not mean that one
is focusing on another object because
the thing in front of you that you look
at is not what the term is whome or
unome so the shift is in the sign which
is in the other direction and then you
could be looking at that very same thing
because the sign has now shifted yeah
and and also like it's
um as as we just said it's the mental
state that's the problem
so you can't get rid of the mental state
directly because the mind is not like
your intentions are a result of the
mental stat so you can't kind of get
behind it uh so what you would do is
just not
act any sign that you attend or any
thought that you attend or any action
that you do you make it so that it's
not going with the grain of the whatever
thing is is whatever craving is there
and then indirectly by not providing
with fuel those thoughts would cease
because you're not it's like um the
Buddha described also as uh when flies
are are buzzing around you that has to
be because there's some kind of smell
smell that's attracting them so you
remove the rotten meat mhm and they
might still be kind of going around
because like they
came there's still some lingering smell
let's say
but if you genuinely took away the meat
or whatever it was eventually they're
going to leave they about to go yeah so
but if you then concern yourself with
you know swatting away the Flies and
you're not actually removing the origin
of the problem the origin of the problem
then you're going to maybe kill those
specific flies but then there's always
going to be more yeah so that is the
first thing that the Buddha says like
attends to a different sign yeah but
then he discusses four other ways in
which one can deal with um these
thoughts as well yeah so all of them
would be kind of within that first one
you find like you don't even need to think
find like you don't even need to think
of it as like oh I'm meditating and then
have my eyes closed and then I have this
thought and then I find another thought
it's just throughout your entire life M
like I have some UNH wholesome State
arising and I simply make sure that I
don't go in that direction
specifically I can go everywhere else
except in that direction and then that
brings us to another Point like the
wholesome as as the Su just defined it
said um it didn't say that the
wholesomeness is the mind
of you know outwardly renouncing things
or outwardly be having loving kindness
and outwardly having wisdom it said the
wholesome mind is the mind of non
lust non aversion and non- delusion so
it doesn't mean like in order to not be
deluded I need to go and start reading
dhama or start contemplating dhama
because otherwise I'm deluded or I need
to give things physically like give up
my everything every all my possessions
because otherwise I have lust or I need
to be you know uh being
extra invest extra effort in being
polite to people because otherwise I'm
acting out of aversion no it just means
the absence of that UNH wholesome state
is automatically the wholesome state so
then you move your mind to a wholesome
sign meaning any sign that is not going
to be involved with any of these three
things and again at any time any UNH
wholesome state that you have in your
mind it's always going to be something
specific you can't have like UNH
wholesomeness kind of like ambiguous
like it's just there no it's always it's
always pushing you towards something
yeah and then you can always avoid that
mhm so perhaps it's worth repeating that
when the Buddha discusses wholesome and
un wholesome he always first says avoid
the UN wholesome and then develop the
wholesome yeah it's never the other way
wrong yeah even the four right effort
the order that it comes it says here a
monk uh first so actually there's one Su
that that he gives like a label to each
of the four steps quot the first one is
he prevents unisen un wholesome States
from arising yes that's called restraint
M then he abandons the Arisen un
wholesome States that's called
dispelling he uh gives rise to the
unisen UN wholesome States wholesome
States un wholesome
States that's called um development and
then he protects M the wholesome states
that are already there and that's called
like um protection so
you it has to be
obviously it's like a structural thing
you won't if there is UN holesome there
and you try to cultivate wholesome
directly it's going to be rooted in the
same yeah craving to get rid of the
thing that was bothering you so the
wholesomeness can only come when the UN
wholesomeness is not there anymore cuz
otherwise like we said that's your being
like the UNH wholesomeness is your being
so any choice that you make is going to
be within the within that yeah within
that un wholesome so even the choice to
fabric a loving kindness and and give
all your possessions up or contemplate
dhama that's going to be done with the
UN wholesomeness you can't like get rid
of something by covering it up in that
manner you have to cuz the problem is
always the resistance to the present
feeling so then if you're doing these
things to get rid of the present feeling
to get rid of the present feeling
because you think that that's what the
dhama is like I must get rid of this
pressure that's un wholesome even though
externally quote unquote the it might
look okay the action is looks very
wholesome because look it's it's the
loving kindness and it's the
renunciation and it's the the
contemplation and wisdom that the Buddha
talked about but it's still underlined
by the same uh desire to get rid of of
pain so that's um that's what makes it
wrong MH so like if someone find himself
like with this kind of pressure of
wanting to do something if like he
cannot just say no but look for
something else to do like like feel that
kind of a pressure to I don't know like
whatever like he wants to do if you
canot just say no but want to do
something it will be still rooted in
this kind of pressure whatever he tries
to do yeah yeah you can say that way
like if the mind um if you can't say no
to it
then you can see this is an un wholesome
pressure something that if if you say no
your mind starts
complaining that's an UNH wholesome
pressure so uh but that in of itself
that doesn't mean like
um you need to do something about it
directly you need to make sure that you
don't act out of it like I said that's
how you don't feed it so yeah the Mind
might be wanting to do
something um but as long as you don't do
that that the Mind wants or anything
else that like you will know that's only
something that you can know internally
which actions would be going further
with this pressure and which actions are
kind of neutral it would totally depend
on the present situation it's not
something that you could fix down CU
like I said you might have a sensual
thought and okay going to the park on a
certain occasion for most people most of
the time you you could say that would be
an action that won't be proliferating
the Central State further but maybe deep
down you know that when you go to the
park there's going to be you know
Attractive people there or whatever so
you can't even fix that as because there
might be a case where now let's say this
first time you went to the park it
wasn't rooted in centrality but then
when you went there you actually
encountered uh you know sensually
pleasing things so now the next time uh
your mind is
like going to the park is going to be
one of the things that your mind wants
to do on account of sensuality so now
you you can't give into that so it's
always dependent on uh yeah on what
is in the present situation only you for
yourself would be able to know as I as I
already repeated whether you act it out
or not and it it always basically
requires you to be on guard because it
might sound as if on one level
um you know I'm talking about how people
would be too wound up with trying to
avoid everything so then it might sound
like this is a more relaxed approach
which yes you kind of relax yourself
from doing the stuff that doesn't matter
but on the level that matters it's
actually more strict M because then you
you are forced to like if there is that
UNH wholesome State there's absolutely
no justification
you there there's no um there's no
extenuating circumstance where you can
give into it and say oh but that wasn't
un wholesome no if you give in you are
acting out of un wholesome so but with a
rule when you take it on the level of
external rules and stuff there can
always be exceptions like even in the in
the v like in some situation if it's
like this or if it's like that well then
it's not an offense but with this it's
not like if there is the UN wholesome
State and you acted out of it that's it
nothing else needs to be considered that
was an unome intention that is the more
fundamental criteria yeah and that's
even I remember some had difficulty
remembering all these rules and he went
to the Buddha and then uh and then the
Buddha said well do you see wholesome
and un wholesome yes then the Buddha say
just don't act out of un wholesome by
Body speech and mind can you do that yes
the monk says and then the suta ends by
saying that monk didn't do anything in
also yeah
yeah initially there was no no rules who
will basically follow that principle in
general yeah and it's it's U you start
off by having these precepts and you
know on some you have to start somewhere
so you will be start starting with the
avoidance of uh UNH wholesome States um
sorry of uh external behaviors because
practically speaking if you haven't been
keeping the precepts mhm there will most
certainly also be UNH wholesome yes uh
pressures making you want to break them
mhm like when you starting out so kind
of by accident almost like without
really seeing the level where in
wholesome wholesome and un wholesome is
you would still kind of be withdrawing
yourself from it just by keeping the
precepts initially mhm then there will
come a point where
you like keeping the precept is not
painful anymore it's not really taking
you taking effort so then you need to
start looking further and see that now
um now keeping the precepts in and of
itself like because there isn't that
pressure anymore to break them
meaning the pressure needs to have moved
somewhere else now unless you're in Arun
there must be something else now that
your mind is pushing you to do and you
might be justifying it as this is fine
because it's look I'm not breaking any
rules yeah so then what would be like
can we say that that only then for
example hindon speaking to come into
sight yeah exactly so at that point like
you might that and that that's actually
a point that many monks and and people
in general who take on the practice of
renunciation might not uh go beyond like
you know you might think oh because I'm
I'm already celibate I'm already
restrained so there's a I don't know the
monks are having a a meeting at at 5:00
p.m. to drink tea and just chat and
socialize and you would think well all
of us are you know Cate living in this
community we don't talk about UNH
wholesome things we don't talk about uh
sensuality but you know but you could go
there out of the desire to the lightting
company for example but is a more subtle
form of un wholesome yeah so then then
it would be UNH wholesome even if
everyone is is you know perfectly well
behaved and stuff um because there is
that pressure it would be obviously a a
more subtle form but it's still the same
the same thing as the Buddha said it's
even like um like a
little uh if you take a how did you say
with your finger fingernail you a little
bit of excrement uhhuh it smells just as
bad as a Full Bucket mhm so even these
very subtle things you can't you can't
justify them
because um it's
it's like just by doing that that would
already prevent you from the basic saati
like saati is knowing wholesome is
wholesome and un wholesome as un
wholesome so then by doing these things
you're basically like not even trying to
look further
by seeing well there's there's more to
that principle of wholesome and
wholesome that I'm not seeing uh so you
would just be believing that
because this is kind of a uh a thing
that all monks would agree is good or
something then uh it's it's not bad so
but that that's not really developing
the no it would be a form of it would be
a form of waiting like as long as I stay
within the boundaries of these precepts
sooner sooner or later that's going to
happen happened to me yeah some sort of
like a magical waiting waiting for it to
come to you like things like a fac takes
place just on account of keeping the
precepts yeah that itself would be
actually one of the first three fets
that precisely prevents the soop yeah
yeah so and and speaking about that
that's why uh it said in the sutas that
that soop is the one who knows wholesome
is wholesome and un wholesome is UN
wholesome and in other places it's and
the root of theol the root yeah uh
because in other places also said that
without grasping the sign of the mind
it's impossible for a person to get the
right View and so then it says without
uh delighting in seclusion if they still
Delight in company it's impossible that
they will U get to see the sign of the
mind because it's not like some um
mystical revelation of image or or
perception that comes to you it's the
recognition of those intent like the
recognition of
those uh impulses let's call it that way
uh that are that are motivating you to
do stuff aana is or a person who a
person gains
STI by being able to see those
intentions and then or those background
States and then there that's where you
get to see the formable truths when the
S say um he sees as it is
uh what is suffering what is the origin
of suffering what is the sensation of
suffering where's the path leading to
the sensation of suffering as it is
doesn't mean like um sometimes it would
get translated as it truly is or as it
really is like you get some sort of hi
yeah but just not like hidden revelation
but no it just means you had these
intentions there and when you were
contemplating what suffering was or what
craving was it was Al always kind of
over there like MH you weren't seeing
this stuff while it was there this this
kind of background mental attitudes you
were not seeing craving on that level so
that's the only place where it can be
seen yeah exactly so then you were you
were thinking oh the craving is like I
like I said you start like that you you
would have started by thinking oh
craving is when I go out and do this
things but no craving is that background
attitude of the mind so recognizing that
background attitude of the mind is
seeing the sign of the Mind and that's
why that's uh indispensable like
literally you absolutely cannot become a
salab without seeing that because
anything that you think craving is won't
be craving because it will be basically
like secondary you might be able to see
what most people are seeing usually it's
the the when they think of craving is
like already further down the line where
those attitudes come like they might
think of all these thoughts and these um
agitation that I experien and then they
might get rid of it by doing a
relaxation meditation technique but all
of that arose in the first place because
you didn't see the background attitude
of your mind you acted out of it and
that led to all this particular
disturbance coming up but if you had
seen that from the very start mhm then
nothing like you wouldn't be able to
overlook even if you wanted to that
acting out of this is not for your
benefit because it's like who on Earth would
because it's like who on Earth would
think that like if you let a child
that's already spoiled and is throwing a
tantrum who on Earth would think that
just letting it keep going that
direction is going to result in
something good it just becomes
immediately apparent that no that there
is no benefit that can come from me
giving into this so then um that's
why the Buddha said if you see one Noble
Truth you see all of them because it's
all about seeing all of it just becomes
apparent when you see oh what am I
actually doing here like am I trying to
get rid of pleasure am I trying sorry am
I trying to get more pleasure am I
trying to get rid of pain on that
background level anyone can think that
they already see that like I know when
I'm when I'm lustful angry but if you're
not aab is because there's still more um
depth to that recognition of what it
even means to try to get rid rid of pain
or go for
pleasure can we
like ask like um because you were saying
like seeing the sign sign of the mind is
like a necessary things in order to
recognize what's whome what's unome then
you say like seclusion is like a
necessary basis to see the sign of the
mind can we say can can we clarify like
why like not being into seclusion like
obstruct us from seeing the sign of the
Mind yeah well the the most obvious thing
yeah well the the most obvious thing
that comes to mind is when you live with
a when you're overly involved with other
people what automatically happens is
whether you recognize it or not like
that's what you know peer pressure and
stuff like you regard you would start to
be regarding as good or as or as like
what should be done you would take it on
the level of what these other people are
doing like it's just a natural kind of
human thing that you measure yourself by
what what uh people in your environment
do so that's on the most obvious level
but as well the
the uh kind of problem with being with
the lighting company is that um that
requires you to overlook that background
attitude like the fact that you're
delighting in company in and of itself
already means that you're overlooking
the back tending or the lighting and
something which moves in the other
direction namely you're already like
trying to look away like the there's the
only way that you can delight and
Company is because you want to kind of
get out of this container that is your
experience you want like to get out into
this other thing out there or other
people out there that will sort of give
you some kind of ease the same way as
you might you know drink or or you're
kind of seeking this external to forget
about this or call someone because you
because you feel lonely or something and
so just you know by talking which is
actually different domain speech you
think that you can release the the
mental pressure of being on your own
that's the word yeah you kind of
released the yeah whereas actually you
can't it's just that is the same as
giving in to the child's stum yeah um so
one needs to then recognize yeah like
you know and then but you see this is
because mind can play tricks no no I'm
just calling some want to see how
they're doing yeah well sure that might
be there but there's something even more
fundamental going on there so so this
has to come with the basic sense of
honesty and this is the whole
authenticity uh basically the discussion
feeds into this as well like you can't
be saved by someone else yeah you and
even by your own mind like you need to
have an attitude of almost Perpetual
suspicion yeah like you can't you can't
trust that because your mind is telling
you that my motivation is such and such
it's not your ally mind well but you see
but then that's the thing because if
somebody has established let say that
sense of suspicion that is right here
and now the birth of Sati of like
recollection right or mindfulness as it
is properly translated so rather than
signing up to a 10day group Retreat or
20-day group Retreat or whatever group
Retreat where one assumes I'm going to
learn a method and I'm going to
gradually become more Mindful and aware
that's actually never going to happen
the the the moment you assume that you
can gradually become Mindful and aware
you are already
overlooking the intention that right now
you're giving yourself time in order to
gradually go there whereas whereas what
you want to see is that you have no
choice but to act right here and now and
if you see that you cannot fully trust
your mind but at the same time that you
can develop that mind
then it is that attitude of
suspiciousness which you just coined it
that is what will give rise to the
full-blown mindfulness on the spot and
if somebody has understood just that for
the rest of their life they never need
to go to any group Meditation Retreat
again in order to learn how to be
mindful if that attitude is right they
but see the consequences of this you
will have freed yourself from this whole
religious spiritual circus of
accumulating this that and the other in
order to gradually uh gain uh what you
think is wholesome and it's never going
to happen yeah but the problem is see
that comes with a burden now because
when you go to the retreat or wherever
it might
be like it might be difficult in the
external sense like oh you have to sit
for 15 hours a day or whatever but
nothing even the torture literal
physical torture like the the athetics
back in the Buddha day they could slep
on sleep on um uh beds nails and stuff
and but nothing is more unpleasant in
that kind of deeply unsettling sense
than questioning your own mind like not
going with the grain when it's that
tantrum is there and not going with it
that's the most unpleasant thing so uh
you would free yourself from the
external duty of uh you know following
these practices and stuff but uh at the
expense of right
now like like we mentioned before most
people want to be free from suffering
ASAP like they're not willing to to
accept the fact that that you know the
recognition of what's wholesome might
initially be unpleasant because the mind
doesn't value that direction so um but
see that that's that would free you but
that's not um it doesn't come for free
and it certainly doesn't go in the same
direction that you're used to so you're
going to have to kind of break and when
you break there's always that you know
yeah and it leaves you very much like
you know on your own in it so you're
fully responsible and that can be
overwhelming as well for people you know
to the extent that you were depending on
external safety this is going to feel
unpleasant like because it's it's kind
of
suddenly um like sweeps the floor that
you were sitting on sweep pull pulls the
rock yeah yeah yeah but it's not coming
stay unpleasant yeah of course so
someone needs to understand that it
might be let's say somewhat of a bitter
pill to swallow in the beginning but
when the when that sort of right effort
is put in um then it's not going to stay
unpleasant like that on the contrary
that is where it's going to be that
independence from external circumstances
becomes the foundation of the true
Freedom then
yeah and that's how it ties in with the
authenticity that's why um authenticity
is indispensable for uh for any progress
in dhama because if you are not willing
to always
question your mental
States uh and and question that it
doesn't matter how right it feels for
you to be doing X Y or Z there still
might be gion illusion in it if you're
not willing to take that on then um
which is what authenticity is then uh
you will be
justifying non d as dama you will be
justifying GRE aversion delusion as
non-re non aversion non delusion or at
least certainly you will not uh know it
for sure for what it is you might as it
said in the suta you might like I don't
do anything bad but as a Buddha defined
that's not because the baby also doesn't
do anything bad yeah so that that in of
itself that's not that's not it so only
with that authenticity
you become able to uh recognize again
these these uh or you can at least have
the openness to question yourself
doesn't mean that you will see things
immediately but you will at least be
having again that that suspiciousness
that I mentioned like you whatever you
think is wholesome you don't take it for
granted because if you know what it hols in you
because if you know what it hols in you
should be free from suffering right now
yeah not like I know what's wholesome
and then somehow later on that gives me some
then somehow later on that gives me some
result knowing what's wholesome frees
you from suffering know in the same way
knowing the escape from suffering frees
you from suffering not like I know the
Escape then I do something and then I
get the
Escape understanding wholesome is like
right view really is is where the
freedom is not right knowledge needs to
Red liberation